George Dana Sanders papers M2163
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George Dana Sanders papers
1898-1909
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Sanders, George Dana, 1851-1918
Marc Selvaggio, Bookseller ABAA
M2163
1.5 Linear Feet 2 MSB and 1 flat box
Biographical / Historical
George Dana Sanders (occasionally misspelled George Dana Saunders) was born in Patten, Maine, in 1851. He became a pastor in Gloucerster, Massachusetts, served in the 8th Massachusetts Infantry as Regimental Chaplain during the Spanish-American War, and died in 1918 at the age of 67.
Content Description
The materials consist primarily of incoming and outgoing personal correspondence in the form of manuscript letters (approximately 200), but also includes typed correspondence, printed orders, telegrams, receipts, and the book Twelve Months with the Eighth Massachusetts Infantry in the service of the United States, by Harry E. Webber (Salem, Mass, 1908). The subject matter primarily focuses on the period of George Sanders' service with the 8th Massachusetts, from 1898-1899, with a few letters from later years. Commissioned as Regimental Chaplain in April of 1898, Sanders was first stationed with the Regiment at Chickamauga, Georgia, then Lexington, Kentucky. He resigned his commission in October 1898, but on January 6, 1899, he was re-appointed Chaplain. He then set out to re-join the 8th Massachusetts now stationed in Matanzas, Cuba. He served in Cuba as both chaplain and on special duty until he was mustered out in April 1899.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford Libraries in 2016.
Sanders, George Dana, 1851-1918; Marc Selvaggio, Bookseller ABAA
- Manuscript letters to Reverend George Dana Sanders from mother, brother L. W. (?) Sanders and from nephew (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters to Reverend George Dan Sanders from Lars (?), B. M. Wonson and Fred Wonson, and from, Charles Dougle (?), manuscript (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters to Reverend George Dan Sanders, mostly manuscript, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters to Reverend George Dan Sanders, mostly manuscript, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters to Reverend George Dan Sanders, mostly manuscript; two manuscript letters, undated, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letters to Reverend George Dan Sanders, official, including from War Department, special orders, and others; typescript (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Requests to Reverend Dana Sanders, Headquarters Dist of Matanzas, Cuba, with multiple endorsements, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence from Reverend George Dana Sanders (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence approving leave, authorizing to remain in Matanzas, and regarding resignation of Reverend George Dana Sanders (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Two manuscripts in Spanish with letterhead La Resp. Logia Los Puritanos; one manuscript in Spanish; handwritten certificate of marriage performed by Reverend Dana Sanders; two leave permissions (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Canceled stamped envelopes (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Ephemera: blank Chatanooga Savings Bank book and check receipts, memorandum of books sent, bill of lading and other receipts, newspaper clipping of Chaplain Sanders leave of absence, General order no. 1 from Camp at Framingham, May 3, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Food distributions, invoices, receipts (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Telegrams to Reverend George Dana Sanders (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Newspaper clippings from The Boston Globe, bulk (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Twelve months with the eight Mass. infantry by Harry E. Webber, Salem, Mass, 1908, with mentions of George Sanders or others of importance marked on pp 106, 126, 140, 154
- Proclamation by Roger Wolcott, governor of Commonwealth of Mas. to commission George D. Sanders as Chaplain of the Eight Regiment Massachusetts Infantry, 1899-01-03 (Flat-box 3)
- List of Colby Alumni, resident of Boston and vicinity, 1902-1903 (Flat-box 3)
- Aid statistics from the United States (Flat-box 3)